Guide to the Elizabeth Mills Brown Files on New Haven Architecture
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Elizabeth Mills Brown files on New Haven architecture
1960-2001
1967-1976
MS 1946
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4
(4 boxes)
Elizabeth Mills Brown was an architectural historian whose life work focused on the architecture of New Haven, Connecticut, and surrounding areas. This collection consists of writings, maps, photographs, reports, and notes that she created and amassed in the course of her extensive research on the architecture and built environment of New Haven and Connecticut. It includes her Yale master's thesis on Center Church on the Green in New Haven; early, annotated drafts, "itineraries," and notes on her book, New Haven: A Guide to Architecture and Urban Design; and reports that she wrote on Wooster Square in cooperation with the New Haven Trust for Historic Preservation. The collection also includes a number of research files for unrealized articles, as well as drafts of several unpublished manuscripts.
Brown, Elizabeth Mills
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lauren Brown, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Elizabeth Mills Brown was born on November 28, 1916. She received a bachelor of fine arts degree from Bennington College in 1939, and a master's degree in art history, specializing in architectural history, from Yale University in 1963 (advised by Carroll L. V. Meeks). Her major work, New Haven: A Guide to Architecture and Urban Design (Yale University Press, 1976), is the authoritative manual on significant New Haven buildings. Brown also researched and wrote several historic survey reports on New Haven neighborhoods, most significantly Wooster Square; wrote a number of articles on Connecticut architects and buildings for various encyclopedias and other publications; and gave regular lectures at the New Haven Colony Historical Society on the history of New Haven's built environment. She was a charter member of the New Haven Preservation Trust, a founding member of the Connecticut Trust for Historic Preservation and the Guilford Preservation Alliance, and a member of the Society of Architectural Historians. She received many awards, including the Connecticut Society of Architects/American Institute of Architects Lay Person Award. At the time of her death, on December 27, 2008, she was compiling an architectural survey of the state of Connecticut as part of the Society of Architectural Historians' series Buildings of the United States.
Scope and Contents
Elizabeth Mills Brown was an architectural historian whose life work focused on the architecture of New Haven, Connecticut, and surrounding areas. This collection consists of writings, maps, photographs, reports, and notes that she created and amassed in the course of her extensive research on the architecture and built environment of New Haven and Connecticut. It includes her Yale master's thesis on Center Church on the Green in New Haven; early, annotated drafts, "itineraries," and notes on her book, New Haven: A Guide to Architecture and Urban Design; and reports that she wrote on Wooster Square in cooperation with the New Haven Trust for Historic Preservation. The collection also includes a number of research files for unrealized articles, as well as drafts of several unpublished manuscripts.
Brown's style of notetaking is exhaustive, including extensive bibliographical references, and there is a great deal of internal cross-referencing between research files. The small amount of correspondence in the files is primarily between Brown and her publishers, with occasional letters of appreciation from readers.
Arrangement
Arrangement of the papers is in two series: I. Writings. II. Files, Lectures and Notebooks.
Architecture -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Wooster Square (New Haven, Conn.); Brown, Elizabeth Mills; Town, Ithiel, 1784-1844; First Church in New Haven (New Haven, Conn.)
- Writings, 1959-1999; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Consists of drafts, unpublished manuscripts, articles, and other writings, including research notes and itineraries for New Haven: A Guide to Architecture and Urban Design, as well as Brown's master's thesis, written under the advisement of Carroll L. V. Meeks in the Yale Department of Art History. Also includes research notes and drafts for manuscripts on Wooster Square and various other publications.
  - Master's Thesis: "The Architects of Center Church"
    - Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Research notes, Circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - "First version for CLVM", Circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - New Haven: A Guide to Architecture and Urban Design
    - Corrections, Circa 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, Circa 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Draft itineraries
      - Topographical and architectural note, Circa 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - "Interstate", Circa 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - "Middletown-State", Circa 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - "Hartford Turnpike-Whitney", Circa 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - "Derby", Circa 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - "Mfd Turnpike-Post Road", Circa 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - "The Green and Downtown", Circa 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - "Yale", Circa 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - "Hillhouse Ave.", Circa 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - "Orange St. and vicinity", Circa 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - "Prospect Hill", Circa 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - "Winchester", Circa 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - "Wooster Square", Circa 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - "Fair Haven", Circa 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Prospectus, Circa 1970 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Reviews and publicity, Circa 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Wooster Square
    - The Historic Houses of Wooster Square: An Introduction to the History of Wooster Square and its Architecture: A Portfolio of Houses Built Before 1880, New Haven Preservation Trust, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Draft manuscript, The Historic Houses of Wooster Square, Circa 1969 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - An Introduction to the History of Wooster Square and its Architecture, 1825-1880, New Haven Preservation Trust, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Draft chapter on Abraham Bishop/Wooster Square land, Circa 1969 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Draft Wooster Square article, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Research files, Circa 1969 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Historic designation survey on Wooster Square, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Articles
    - Macmillan Encyclopedia of American Art Before 1914, drafts of entries, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Praeger Encyclopedia, drafts of entries, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Brockett article drafts and correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Journal of the New Haven Colony Historical Society, "John Brockett of New Haven: The Man and the Myth", 1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Unpublished manuscripts and manuscript fragments
    - Manuscript fragments: Federal - Urban, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Manuscript fragments: Jacksonian period, Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Manuscript fragments: Edwardian, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Notes on unpublished New Haven Colonial manuscript, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - Draft, "Architecture and Urbanism in New Haven", Circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Unpublished "Blue Manuscript", Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Unpublished manuscript: "The Colonial Period: A New Plantation Whose Design is Religion", Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Notes and unpublished Hillhouse draft, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Unpublished manuscript: David Hoadley, Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Unpublished "London Manuscript", written with George Hersey [includes EMB note on all unpublished manuscripts], Circa 1968 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Unpublished "Ozzie Manuscript" [Colonial Urban], Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Files, lectures and notebooks, Circa 1919-2001; Series II
  Consists of Brown's research files (which she compiled in notebooks), lecture files, correspondence, and general notes. Most of the folder names in this series are drawn directly from Brown's own folder titles. The notebooks represent various projects and ideas Brown continued to work on throughout her career, and served as her own idiosyncratic but exhaustive historical reference works. The notebooks on New Haven: A Guide to Architecture and Urban Design end abruptly with "O."
  - Correspondence, general, 1976-2001 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Curriculum vitae, Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Files, notes, and lectures, Circa 1970-1990
    - Edgehill, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Includes slides.
    - New Haven Architectural Club historical exhibition programs, Circa 1919-1929 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Chaplin Street (Chaplin, CT) and others, for talks at Guilford Library and Connecticut League, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Connecticut League, Guilford Library, and Whitney Center talks, Circa 1994-1996 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Hartford research material, Circa 1970-1990 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Moore-Grover-Harper, notes and illustrations, 1981 April 13 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Preservation movement in Connecticut, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
    - Rochester talk on preservation movement, 1981 May 21 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Society of Architectural Historians meeting in New Haven, 1982 April (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - John Trumbull lecture at Yale Art Gallery, 1982 November 14 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Dorothy Whitfield-Hyland House talk, Guilford, 1983 June 1 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - General files and lectures, 1972-1995 (Box 3, Folder 16-20)
    - Files and tours, Circa 1993 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Notes on planned Guilford survey, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Notebooks
    - Bibliography, Undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Churches paper for Meeks, Undated (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
    - Colonial, Undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Federal (Early Republic), Undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Jacksonian, Undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Lost New Haven, Undated (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
    - New Haven, preface-introduction, A-D, Circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - New Haven, E-F, Circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - New Haven, G, Circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - New Haven, H, Circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - New Haven, I, Circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - New Haven, J, Circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - New Haven, K, Circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - New Haven, L-M, Circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - New Haven, N, Circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - New Haven, O, Circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - NYC Churches, Undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Town, Ithiel, Undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Miscellaneous notes and do's, Undated (Box 4, Folder 22)